John James Audubon Collection, 1788-1970: Finding Aid
Princeton University Library. Special Collections.
- Correspondence, 1788-1963; 3 boxes
  - Letters of John James Audubon (Photostat Copies), 1807 April 29-1843 June 13; 27 folders
    - Photostat Copy of Letter to Victor G. Audubon, Fort Clark, 1843 June 6; 1 folder (Folder 84)
    - Photostat Copy of Letter to Victor G. Audubon, Fort Union, 1843 June 13; 1 folder (Folder 85)
  - Letters of Others (Photostat Copies), 1825 January 4-1918 February; 8 folders
    Consists of photostat copies of letters primarily from Victor Audubon and John Bachman.
    - Photostat Copy of Victor G. Audubon Letter to J. T. Bowen, New York, 1847 April 14; AM 18786; 1 folder (Folder 86)
      Photocopy of B2 F55. Original acquired by PUL in 1965.
    - Photostat Copy of Victor G. Audubon Letter to John Bohlen, New York, 1854 May 11; 1 folder (Folder 87)
      Photocopy of B2 F56. Original acquired by PUL in 1965.
    - Xerox Copies of Victor G. Audubon Letters to S. F. Baird; and Lucy Audubon to Joseph Henry, 1850 November 21-1863 December 29; 1 item (Folder 88)
      Originals in Smithsonian Institution, Washington, D.C.
    - Photostat Copy of John Bachman Letter to Joseph N. Bevan, Charleston, S.C., 1825 January 4; 1 folder (Folder 89)
      Photocopy of B2 F57. Original acquired by PUL in 1965.
    - Transcripts of John James Audubon Letters to Richard Harlan and J. K. Townsend, 1827-1838; 1 folder (Folder 90)
      Transcripts of originals in Gilbert Collection, College of Physicians, Philadelphia.
    - Photostat Copies of Francis Hobart Herrick 3 Letters to Edward H. Johnson, 1918 February; 1 folder (Folder 91)
      3 letters regarding Audubon's Quadrupeds. Photocopies of B2 F59. Original acquired by PUL in 1965.
    - Photostat Copies of John Bachman Letters to John K. Townsend, Charleston, S.C., 1838-1842; 1 folder (Folder 92)
    - Transcripts of John James and Lucy Audubon Letters to Mrs. C. C. Adams, 1864 January 27; 1 folder (Folder 93)
      Originals in Vodges Collection, Science Libr. Natural Hist. Museum, Balboa Pk., San Diego, California.]
- Howard Corning Transcripts of Audubon's Letters and Journals, 1820-1937; AM 17903; 6 volumes
  Consists of six bound volumes containing typed transcripts of Audubon's letters and journals, edited by Howard Corning for three books published by The Club of Odd Volumes: Letters of John James Audubon, 1826-1840 (1930), Journal of John James Audubon Made During his Trip to New Orleans in 1820-1821 (1929), and Journal of John James Audubon made while obtaining subscriptions to his "Birds of America" 1840-1843 (1929). These volumes also include transcripts of letters from Lucy Audubon and V. G. Audubon, printed materials, notes on editorial policy, and other items that are not in Corning's printed volumes.
  Gift of the National Audubon Society in 1964.
  - Howard Corning Transcripts of Audubon's Letters, 1826-1831; 1 volume
  - Howard Corning Transcripts of Audubon's Letters, 1831-1835; 1 volume
  - Howard Corning Transcripts of Audubon's Letters, 1835-1841; 1 volume
  - Howard Corning Transcripts of Audubon's Letters, 1821-1937; 1 volume
    Includes Audubon letters (1841-1845), as well as later letters to John Bachman and some printed materials.
  - Howard Corning Transcripts of Audubon's Journals, 1820-1821; 1 volume
  - Howard Corning Transcripts of Audubon's Journals, 1840-1845; 1 volume
- Audubon as Subject, 1836-1970; 1 box
  Consists of miscellaneous printed material such as pamphlets, brochures, exhibition and dealer catalogues, and clippings about John James Audubon, as well as correspondence and subject files on related topics. Much of this material was gathered by Dr. Howard C. Rice, Jr., of Princeton University Library and relates to his research on Audubon and the whereabouts of his prints, manuscripts, and paintings.
  - Articles, Clippings, and Pamphlets, 1936-1969; 1 folder (Folder 1)
  - Exhibition Catalogues, 1951-1965; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Havell, Engraver, 1928-1964; 1 folder (Folder 3)
  - Elephant Folio, Princeton University Library Copy, 1929-1970; 1 folder (Folder 4)
  - List of Plates; Census of Elephant Folio, 1932-1969; 1 folder (Folder 5)
  - Engraved Plates, Dealers, Catalogues with Price-lists, 1929-1968; 1 folder (Folder 6)
  - Key West, Florida, 1960s; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Information about Items in Princeton Collections, 1836-1954; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Reproductions of Engraved Prints, 1960s; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Catalogues of Manuscripts and Letters, 1953-1964; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - Note about Setter and Quails, undated; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - "Mill Grove" Audubon House in Pennsylvania, 1953-1964; 1 folder (Folder 12)
  - Audubon Portraits of Elijah Slack & Wife, 1964; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - Portraits of Audubon, 1959-1962; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  - Oil Paintings, 1951-1968; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - Obituary by T. M. Brewer, in Boston Atlas, 1851; 1 folder (Folder 16)
- "The World of John James Audubon" Exhibition, 1959-1960; 2 boxes
  Consists of correspondence, catalogues, publicity, research notes, and a card index related to Princeton University Library's 1959 exhibition on "The World of John James Audubon." Many of these materials were created or assembled by Dr. Howard C. Rice, Jr.
  - Correspondence with Darthea Speyer, United States Information Service, Paris, Regarding Paris Exhibition, 1960; 1 folder (Folder 1)
    Also includes a catalogue, notes, clippings, and poster.
  - Lists of Items Borrowed, 1959 May 15-September; 1 folder (Folder 2)
  - Correspondence A - E, 1959-1960; 1 folder (Folder 3)
    Includes: Sylvia Beach, Geo. Dock, Jr.
  - Correspondence F - L, 1959-1960; 1 folder (Folder 4)
    Includes: Alice Ford, W. H. Fries, Harvard.
  - Correspondence M - N, 1959-1960; 1 folder (Folder 5)
    Includes: McCormick, H. Bradley Martin, National Audubon Society-NY, New Jersey Audubon Society, Harry Shaw Newman-old printshop, J. d'Arcy Northwood-curator, Audubon Shrine.
  - Correspondence O - Z, 1959-1960; 1 folder (Folder 6)
    Includes: Benj. Page, Jr., Darthea Speyer (USIS, Paris), Stout, J. S. Williams.
  - Press Release, Publicity, and Talks by Howard C. Rice, Jr., 1959; 1 folder (Folder 7)
  - Thomas Birch Painting of Mill Grove, 1959; 1 folder (Folder 8)
  - Leaflet Sketches and Drafts, 1959; 1 folder (Folder 9)
  - Research Notes for Catalogue: II & Supporting Documentation, 1959; 1 folder (Folder 10)
  - Research Notes for Catalogue: IV, V, VI., 1959; 1 folder (Folder 11)
  - Research Notes for Catalogue: VII, 1959; 1 folder (Folder 12)
    N.J. paper money cf. no. 44.
  - Research Notes for Catalogue: VIII - IX., 1959; 1 folder (Folder 13)
  - Research Notes for Catalogue: X, 1959; 1 folder (Folder 14)
  - Research Notes for Catalogue: XVI. "Minnie's Land", 1959; 1 folder (Folder 15)
  - Chronological List of Audubon's Bird Drawings, 1959; 1 box
    Consists of a card index, with a note inside that reads: "Based on the List of Plates, comprising the Original Issue of Audubon's 'The Birds of America,' With Notes showing where and when the original drawings were made," in S.C. Arthur, Audubon, 1937, Appendix E., p. 500 ff. Arthur's dating of the drawings is based chiefly on the annotations to be found on the originals, now in N.Y. Historical Society. Present card index compiled by Mrs. Julian P. Boyd, 1959. It was used as a basis for grouping Audubon bird plates according to place & date of the drawing, rather than by date of publication. Audubon exhibition, 1959. H. C. Rice"
- 32101040679084 (Box 6)
- 32101040679043 (Box 1)
- 32101040679050 (Box 2)
- 32101047417801 (Volume 1)
- 32101047417793 (Volume 2)
- 32101047417785 (Volume 3)
- 32101047419013 (Volume 4)
- 32101047417777 (Volume 5)
- 32101047417769 (Volume 6)
- 32101040679068 (Box 3)
- 32101040679076 (Box 4)
- 32101040679092 (Box 5)